我叫乌特雷德，乌特雷德之子
My name is uhtred, son of uhtred.
我生来便是诺森布里亚的郡长
I was born an ealdorman of northumbria.
贝班堡的正统继承人
The rightful heir to bebbanburg.
但命运安排我在丹麦人中长大
But fate decreed I would be raised as a Dane.
那就是我的生活
That was my life
直到我的家人惨遭杀害
until my family was murdered.
外面传言说称我是罪魁祸首
Word was spread that I was to blame.
一个撒克逊奴隶，在婚宴上杀了自己的主人
A Saxon slave, he killed his master at a wedding party.
于是，我和布丽达逃往威塞克斯
And so, with brida, I fled to wessex.
去投奔阿尔弗雷德，他后来成为了国王
To Alfred, a man who would become king.
尽管并非所有人都认可  - 我才是父亲的继承人
Though not all agreed. - I am my father's heir.
我向这位国王宣誓效忠
I swore an oath to this king.
这份誓言让我失去了布丽达，也让我无法
An oath that lost me brida and prevented me
去投奔我的兄弟拉格纳
from joining my brother ragnar.
但命运主宰一切
But destiny is all.
你不配成婚
You don't deserve to marry.
那位女士是名门闺秀，你不过是个异教徒
That woman is a lady and you're a heathen.
你就算泡一整天澡，身上还是臭
You could bathe all day, you'd still stink.
你一直盯着我看，小奥达？难不成你想让我娶你？
Have you been watching me, odda the boy? Should I be marrying you?
给你十枚银币，让你离开这里怎么样
Ten pieces of silver for you to walk away.
你父亲知道你在这儿吗？
Does your father know you're here?
十一枚
Eleven pieces.
不如用我这把剑等重的银子来换？
How about my sword's weight in silver?
胡说八道
Nonsense.
那我就娶那姑娘，今晚我还会和她做爱
Then I'll marry the girl. And tonight, I'll plough her.
- 你为何要这样说她? - 也许你想把她据为己有
- Why must you talk of her like that? - Perhaps you'd like her for yourself.
你自己想占有她, 是不是?
You want her beneath you. Am I right?
你这人根本没法讲道理
You're impossible to reason with.
什么事在你眼里都是游戏
Everything is a game.
看在米尔德丝的份上, 我希望你在这儿待的时间不会太久
I hope for mildrith's sake, your time on this earth is short.
你不是郡长
You are not an ealdorman
永远也当不了
and never shall be.
嘿! 这边!
Hey! Here!
我没被允许去见她, 我还没见过她
I wasn't allowed to meet her. I haven't seen her.
规矩就是这样
It is the way.
直到昨天我才知道她的存在
I was unaware of her existence till yesterday.
- 她是不是又朴素又虔诚? - 虔诚是肯定的
- She'll be plain and pious? - Oh, she'll be pious, all right.
要是她是个荡妇, 阿尔弗雷德早就扑上去了
If she was a leg-spreader, Alfred would have been on her by now.
你见过她?
Have you seen her?
远远看了一眼
A distance away.
"朴素"这个词倒是贴切
"Plain" is a fair description.
聘礼给了多少?
How much was the bride price?
三十三枚
Thirty-three pieces.
我得支付给她的教父奥达
Which  I've  paid,  to  her  Godfather  Odda,
我也会确保她收到这笔钱
and which I'll make sure she receives.
我许下过承诺
I've made promises.
复仇之类的
Revenge and such.
你知道你为什么在这里吗?
Why are you here? Do you know?
她给我带来了土地
She brings land.
我会成为阿尔弗雷德麾下的领主, 能积累财富, 聚拢人马
I'll become a lord under Alfred. I'll be able to make wealth, gather men.
- 夺回属于我的东西    - 这些理由已经足够了
- Take back what's mine. - All reasons enough.
朴素不朴素不重要, 她能派上用场就行
Plain or not, she serves her purpose.
你许下的承诺必须兑现
The promises you have made will stand.
血仇可以追一辈子
Blood feuds last a lifetime.
你要做的, 浑球, 就是一天一天地活下去, 直到最后一天
What you do, arseling, is you keep living each day until the last.
神父终于来了, 咱们赶紧把事儿办了
The priest has arrived finally. Let's get this done.
你不必做这件事
You do not need to "get this done."
我会去向阿尔弗雷德求情
I will make a plea to Alfred.
她来了, 感谢主
She's here, praise god.
你站直了, 看起来正经一点, 哪怕人不是很干净
You should stand and look respectful, if not entirely clean.
- 她看起来怎么样?    - 我猜是吓坏了
- How does she look? - Terrified, I bet.
贝奥卡神父, 能不能把仪式简短一点
If you could be brief with the ceremony, father beocca,
我会很感激的, 我还有事要见国王
I'd be grateful. I have business with the king.
新娘已经收到聘礼了吗?
The bride has been given her price?
她会的
She will.
你来作见证
You are witness.
谢谢你, 大人
Thank you, lord.
若两位新人愿意到祭坛前来...
If the betrothed couple would like to join me at the altar...
- 双手相握  - 快点
- And join hands. - Be brief.
愿天上的主垂目怜悯
May god in his heaven look down with mercy
他的虔诚仆人乌特雷德与米尔德丝
upon his devoted servants, uhtred and mildrith.
愿主赐福这对夫妇, 以爱、子嗣与财富
May he bless their union with love, and children, and wealth.
也愿他们时刻感恩颂赞
And may they, in turn, be sure to give thanks and praise,
每日依照主的圣言而活, 阿门
and live each day according to his holy word. Amen.
- 阿门  - 阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
你们在天主的见证下，已结为夫妻
You are now joined as man and wife in the eyes of god.
喜悦的泪水
Tears of joy.
让我来帮你
Allow me to help you with that.
谢谢你，大人
Thank you, lord.
我是个幸运的人...
I'm a lucky man...
能娶到如此美丽的妻子
To have such a beautiful wife.
追求你的人一定不少吧
There must have been many suitors, I'm sure.
你太抬举我了
You're kind to believe so.
我说得对吗?
Am I right?
没有合适的，大人
None suitable, lord.
我叫乌特雷德，叫我乌特雷德就行
My name's uhtred. Call me uhtred.
浑球，该上路了
Arseling, time we were on our way.
或者，你有时候也可以叫我"浑球"
Or from time to time, you may wish to call me "arseling."
大人
Lord.
丹麦人
Danes.
我们为什么停下来?
Why are we stopping?
他们是什么人?
Who are they?
多半是强盗
Foragers, most likely.
- 但终归是丹麦人       - 他们会动手吗?
- But Danes all the same. - Will they attack?
继续走
We walk on.
他们跟上来了
They're following us.
继续走，他们不会动手的
We walk on. They won't attack.
那你为什么拔剑了?
Then why have you drawn your sword?
让他们知道，至少有一个人会死在这里
To show them at least one of them will die.
一个，或者两个
One or two.
- 强盗们已经深入威塞克斯了   - 那是古思伦的人
- Foragers are deep into wessex. - They're guthrum's men.
他们离伦敦有点远
They're a long way from lundene.
大人, 婚礼已经举行了
Lord, the marriage has taken place.
他们现在正在去农庄的路上
They are now on the road to the farmstead.
好消息, 谢谢你, 奥达
Good news. Thank you, odda.
现在看看他如何应对这个挑战
We shall see how he responds to the challenge.
婚事已成, 大人, 我确实担心米尔德丝
Now it is done, lord, I do fear for mildrith.
她得亲口告诉他实情
She will have to give him the facts.
他肯定要冲她发火, 奥达, 这我明白
Oh, he will bark at her, odda, I'm sure.
但他真正的怒火, 是留给你我的
But his real anger will be reserved for you and I.
他不会甘心受天主与国王双重约束
He will not like being beholden to god and to king.
但若他想成为一个真正的郡长
But if he is to become a true ealdorman,
就必须承担这份重担, 这是对他的考验
he must accept his burden. That is the test.
是, 大人
Yes, lord.
米尔德丝是赐给他的美丽慰藉
Mildrith is his beautiful consolation.
他对她动心了吗?
Was he struck by her?
动心了, 大人
He was, lord.
你怎么还没成家?
Why are you not already married?
你这年纪, 早该有两三个孩子了
You're old enough to have had two or three children by now.
浑球大人
Lord arseling.
问这话的时机早过了
There is a time for such questions, and it has past.
阿尔弗雷德为何赐我这样一位美丽的新娘?
Why has Alfred gifted me such a beautiful bride?
我猜是因为欠别人债吧
Has a debt, I'm guessing.
这不是我该说的
It's not my place to tell you.
多少?
How much?
我父亲想在天主面前得蒙恩宠
My father wanted to find favour with god
所以他把十分之一的土地献给了教会
so he devoted a tenth of his land to the church.
教会不拥有这片地, 但有权收取它的出产
They do not own it, but they are entitled to its yield.
实际上他们要求收取出产
Indeed, they demand its yield,
就算庄稼欠收、丹麦人来袭也不例外
even when crops fail and Danes raid.
天主是善的
God is good.
于是主教把我父亲告上了法庭
So the bishop took my father to law.
债务有多少?
How much is the debt?
教会就是法律
The church is the law.
法律裁定我父亲欠了他们一大笔钱
And the law decreed that my father owed to them a huge sum.
- 根本超出了他的还款能力        - 多少钱?
- Quite beyond his ability to pay. - How much?
他不久后就去世了
He died soon after.
是一笔相当大的数目, 大人
It is a substantial amount, lord.
而且每年都在增加
It increases yearly.
阿尔弗雷德本可以免除这笔债, 但他选择不这么做
Alfred could remove the debt. He has chosen not to.
欠款共计两千先令, 大人
The amount owed is 2,000 shillings, lord.
该死的阿尔弗雷德
Damn him.
他所坚守的一切都该死
Damn everything he stands for.
- 该死的他的教会和他的天主     - 大人, 我不喜欢你说这种亵渎的话
- Damn his church and his god. - Lord, I don't like your blasphemy.
我的名字是乌特雷德!
My name is uhtred!
不过我那么晚才看清这一切，叫我"浑球"也行
Though by all means, call me "arseling" for not seeing this sooner.
你的新家
Your new home.
土地不错, 房子需要修缮
The land is good. The buildings need repair.
住在这片地上的几户人家过来向我们道喜
Families who live on the land come to wish us well.
让他们回自己家去
Send them back to their homes.
他们是来给我们送祝福的, 我认识他们一辈子了
They've come to wish us well. I have known them my whole life.
大人, 夫人
Lord. Lady.
奥斯瓦尔德管着这片农庄, 就住在附近
Oswald manages the farmstead. He lives nearby.
欢迎回家, 也请接受我们对你们婚事的美好祝愿
Welcome home. And may we offer our good wishes on your marriage.
谢谢你, 奥斯瓦尔德, 谢谢你们
Thank you, oswald. Thank you.
你们大家特地聚在这里迎接我和我的主君乌特雷德大人, 真是太好了
And how kind of you all to gather to greet me and my lord uhtred.
大人, 我们已经备好了桌席, 请您享用
We have prepared a table, lord, for your pleasure.
谢谢你们的心意, 不过我们累了
You have my thanks, but we're tired.
明白, 大人
Of course, lord.
谢谢你, 奥斯瓦尔德, 你真好
Thank you, oswald. You're kind.
我为每家准备了一份婚礼礼物
I have a wedding gift for each family.
- 是银子       - 谢谢您, 米尔德丝夫人
- It is silver. - Thank you, lady mildrith.
- 感谢你们的善意与忠诚         - 真的太感谢了
- For your kindness and your loyalty. - Thank you so much.
感谢你们在我不在时替我照看这片土地
For taking care of the land in my absence.
哦, 这景象看着真顺眼
Now, there's a welcome sight.
我本以为这里会有一座大厅, 结果就看到这个
I was expecting there to be a hall, and I find this.
把债还清了, 你就能建大厅
Pay off your debts, and you can build a hall.
我没说错吧, 那混蛋很精明的——阿尔弗雷德
Didn't I tell you the bastard thinks? Alfred.
他要是以为能让我低头求他, 那他想得美
If he believes he can make me beg, he can think again.
他不是要你低头, 他要的是你服从
He doesn't want you to beg. He wants you to obey.
绝无可能
Never.
大人, 如果您不需要我了, 我去歇着了
If you have need for me, lord, I'll be resting.
我确实累了
It seems I am tired.
我欠教会两千先令的债，你倒把银子分给你的佃户
I'm 2,000 shillings in debt to the church, and you hand out silver to your tenants.
那是我的银子
It is my silver.
- 你可以拿走我钱袋里的钱      - 我不要你钱袋里的钱
- Have what's in my purse. - I don't want what's in your purse.
那你为何要骂我?
Then why scold me?
那个白胖子, 你庄子上的管事
The stoat. Your farmstead master.
- 奥斯瓦尔德   - 得盯紧他
- Oswald. - He'll need to be watched.
- 他是我父亲信任的人   - 他活得太滋润了
- He was trusted by my father. - He lives too well.
- 我正要去谷仓     - 你可以睡在屋里
- I'm on my way to the barn. - You can sleep in the house.
我更喜欢谷仓, 谢谢
I prefer the barn. Thank you.
今晚可是你们的新婚之夜
It is your wedding night.
夫人, 晚安
Good night, lady.
浑球
Arseling.
我可以走了吗?
May I leave now?
你收了多少银子作为聘礼?
How many pieces of silver did you receive as your price?
十八块
Eighteen.
这数目对吗?
Is that correct?
- 聘礼是三十三块    - 我相信这只是个疏失
- The price was 33. - I'm sure it was an honest mistake.
你被骗了
You were robbed,
就像我也被骗了一样
as I was robbed.
那笔钱是你的保障, 你会拿到全部, 一分不少
That price is your security, and you will have it, all of it.
我可以去歇息了吗?
May I rest?
大人, 很抱歉今天让您失望了
I'm sorry the day has been a disappointment for you, lord.
你心地很好
You have a good heart.
还把自己的银子送出去
Gifting your silver.
奥达还欠你十五块, 我会让他补上
Odda owes you 15 pieces more. I'll see that he pays.
这笔债务不是你的过错, 我不怪你
And the debt's not something I blame you for.
阿尔弗雷德欺骗了我, 我当初该更谨慎的
It's Alfred's deceit. I should have been wiser.
只是你让我迷了眼
Though I was blinded by you.
你该吃点东西
You should eat.
我也该吃点，但我不想一个人吃
I should eat. But I don't want to eat alone.
天主让我成为你的妻子
God has made me your wife.
这其中必有缘由
There must be a reason.
天主是慈善的
God is good.
你在看什么
What is it you're looking at?
那片土地上有一道伤痕
There's a scar across the land there.
是丹麦人的行军长龙，没有尽头
The never-ending line of Danes on the march.
拉格纳
Ragnar.
等消息传到阿尔弗雷德那里，早就来不及了
By the time word reaches Alfred, it would be too late.
除非他们长了翅膀
They would need wings.
奥斯瓦尔德，那个方向是什么城镇
Oswald, what town lays in that direction?
如果他们继续往西走，一两天后
If they keep going west, in a day or so,
就会到达沃勒姆的要塞
they'll come to the fortress at wareham.
带上你的家人和其他人躲进山里，等他们过去，快去
Take your family and the others to the hills till they've passed. Do it now.
- 米尔德丝夫人呢？ - 她跟我一起走...
- And the lady mildrith? - She travels with me...
去温彻斯特
To Winchester.
是，大人
Yes, lord.
你看到多少人
How many do you see?
问题是，还会有多少人跟来
The question is, how many will follow?
威塞克斯正在遭到入侵，而我们却被告知等着，等他祈完祷
Wessex is being invaded and we're told to wait while he prays.
天主是他的力量，乌特雷德
God is his strength, uhtred.
他现在该上马冲阵，不是跪在地上祈祷
He needs to be on horseback, not on his knees.
- 我讨厌这个地方   - 越来越糟了
- I hate this place. - It grows worse.
没人告诉我你在这里, 真叫人高兴
I was not told you were here. How pleasing.
- 大人    - 没想到你不是一个人（怀孕了）
- Lord. - And so much of you.
他准备好了吗?
Is he ready?
国王已准备就绪, 贤人会议也是
The king is ready, as is his council.
你眼睁睁看着三百多个丹麦人大摇大摆地穿越威塞克斯
You watched 300 men or more march clean across wessex
却什么都没做?
and you did nothing?
我来这里了
I'm here.
派个信使来就够了
A messenger could have been sent in your place.
- 一个小孩都行    - 你为何不和这些丹麦人对峙?
- A boy. - Why did you not confront these Danes?
你手下有兵, 你的职责就是培养战士
You have men. That's your purpose, to create warriors.
我只有二十个士兵和他们的妻子, 大多数还在种地
I've been given 20 men and wives, most work the fields.
和丹麦人作战就是送死，大人
It would've been a slaughter, lord.
但你选择了不战
But you chose not to fight.
我们也没法知道结果了
We'll never know.
战士只能死一次, 为何要白白送命?
A warrior can only die once. Why die in vain?
这些丹麦人是从伦敦或东盎格利亚过来的
The Danes have travelled from either lundene or east anglia.
难道没有人盯着他们?
Were they not being watched?
我们一直在监视停在泰晤士河上的船, 这是个失误
We have been watching the ships which remain on the tames. A mistake.
沃勒姆一旦被占, 战船就会接踵而来
If wareham is captured, ships will follow.
三百人会变成三千人
Three hundred men will become 3,000.
- 我的建议是立刻出兵    - 国王没有向你讨教
- My advice is we march without delay. - I don't recall the king seeking advice.
你亲眼看到了多少丹麦人?
How many Danes did you witness?
远不止两百, 而且个个都是战士
More than 200 by far. Warriors to a man.
沃勒姆恐怕挡不住他们
Wareham will struggle to hold them back.
和平就此终结
The peace is over.
我们别无选择, 只能率兵前往沃勒姆
We have no choice but to march on wareham
祈求天主保佑我们在城堡陷落前赶到
and pray god we arrive before the fortress falls.
大人, 您认为这是一次大规模入侵?
You believe it is an invasion, lord?
很可能是丹麦大军的先兆, 没错
It could well be the beginning of a great Dane army, yes.
会议到此结束, 威塞克斯各位郡长, 整备兵马
Council is over. Ealdormen of wessex, prepare your men.
贝奥卡神父, 出发前我要做祈祷
Father beocca, I shall pray before we leave.
是, 大人
Yes, my lord.
神父, 我想私下觐见国王
Father, I wish to speak to the king privately.
我去通禀
I will ask,
但要我说, 你还得好好学学规矩
but I note that you are still to learn respect.
奥达郡长, 如果我可以说几句
Ealdorman odda, if I may speak out.
你还欠我妻子一半的聘礼
You owe my wife half of her bride-price.
我付了三十三块银子, 她只收到十八块
I paid 33 pieces of silver. She received only 18.
她说这是个无心之失
An honest mistake, she assures me.
是这样吗?
Is this true?
把钱补上
Pay him.
整备人马, 向沃勒姆进发
Ready the men to march on wareham.
你知道吗, 和米尔德丝做爱很愉快
You should know mildrith is a joy to plough.
你就是个异教徒
You're a heathen.
而你是个处男
And you're a virgin.
我才不是
No, I'm not.
他就是
Yes, he is.
怎么了?
What is it? Hm?
答应我, 你一定要平安回来
Promise me you will come back safely.
两条胳膊, 两只耳朵, 一个都不少
Two arms, both ears.
答应我
Promise me.
我会尽力的
I‘ll do my best.
但你也得答应我同样的事
But only if you do the same.
如果他们来了, 别躲在教堂或修道院里, 去山上, 去林子里
If they come, don't shelter in a church or nunnery. Go to the hills, the woods.
我会来的
I'll come.
为了你们两个
For both of you.
浑球
Arseling.
亲她一下, 咱们该走了
Kiss her and let's be on our way.
米尔德丝, 亲爱的, 我们一直在找你
Mildrith, my dear, we've been looking for you.
埃尔斯威斯夫人, 见到你真好, 看你这气色, 真是好极了
My lady aelswith. How good to see you, and to see you looking as you do.
这孩子就是不肯老实待着
It refuses to keep still.
- 我这个也一样    - 唉, 咱们受的这罪
- Mine is the same. - Oh, how we suffer.
愿主保佑我们都能平安
I pray we both survive.
愿主保佑我们四个都能平安
I pray we four survive.
天主会说了算的
God will decide.
我好想你, 米尔德丝, 每天都为你祈祷
I've missed you, mildrith, and I prayed for you each day.
- 可怜的孩子  - 可怜什么?
- Poor thing. - Why poor?
跟那个强塞给你的男人住在一起, 一个异教徒
Living with the man they foisted onto you, the pagan.
还得承受他的那些事
Having to take his seed and the like.
乌特雷德是个好人, 他待我很好
Uhtred is decent. He treats me well.
真的很好
He does.
天主会因你的忠诚而赐福于你
God will bless your loyalty.
但但愿他能很快战死沙场
But with luck, he will fall in battle, and soon.
快告诉我你饿了
Please tell me that you're hungry.
- 我有点饿    - 去厨房找我
- I am a little. - Meet me in the kitchens.
我已经为孕妇备好了一顿饭
I have arranged a meal for the pregnant.
但别急着祷告
But do not rush prayers.
不不, 当然不会, 呵
No. No. Of course not. Heh.
主啊, 他不是你最谦卑虔诚的仆人
Lord, he is not your most humble or devout servant.
但我祈求你能...
But I pray...
保他平安
Keep him safe.
让他完成你的旨意
Let him do your work.
让他亲眼看见自己的孩子
Let him see his child.
我很高兴今天见到你的妻子
I was pleased to see your lady today, your wife.
而且她怀着孩子
And carrying a child.
这是天主的恩赐
It's god's blessing.
感觉就像昨天的事一样
It seems like only yesterday
我先给你施洗, 取名奥斯伯特, 后来又改名乌特雷德
I was baptising you as osbert, and then again as uhtred.
你想和国王谈什么事?
What is it you wish to speak about with the king?
那是我和国王之间的事
It's between myself and the king.
他关注着你, 乌特雷德
He's watching you, uhtred.
- 天主？ - 阿尔弗雷德
- God?   - Alfred
看你怎么行事, 以国王的身份评判你
Watching how you behave, judging you as a lord
他没有资格评判我
He has no right to judge.
他是国王
He's a king.
他在婚事上骗了我
He lied to me regarding the marriage.
你说的是那笔债吗?
Are you referring to the debt?
- 你知道这件事? - 这不是秘密
- You know of it? - It's not a secret.
我劝你表现出你已经接受了
And I urge you to show him you accepted,
尤其是那笔债是欠教会的
especially as it is owed to the church.
你必须保持冷静, 乌特雷德, 要懂得敬重
You must remain calm, uhtred, respectful.
大人
My lord.
- 我请求私下... - 你吃过东西了吗?
- I requested a private... - Have you eaten?
有时候我很馋肉食...
There are times when I crave meat...
以及别的东西
And other things.
但我知道那满足感转瞬即逝, 痛苦却会绵延
But I know the gratification would be fleeting, the suffering prolonged,
所以我忍着吃粥
and so I suffer gruel.
不过我夫人不准我叫粥, 非要叫"肉汤"
Though my wife will not allow it to be called anything other than "broth."
你一定会很高兴得知我的细作带来了消息
You will be happy to learn that my spies have news.
- 来自沃勒姆的? - 来自爱尔兰
- From wareham? - From Ireland.
乌巴的兄弟伊瓦尔在那里被杀了, 本来无关紧要
Ivar, brother of ubba, has been killed there, which would be irrelevant,
但乌巴要亲自为他复仇
but for the fact ubba wishes to avenge him personally.
这是真的?
This is true?
海那边一个爱尔兰人杀了个丹麦人, 天下就此变局
An irishman across the sea kills a Dane, and the world changes.
这是天主的旨意
The hand of god.
乌巴会这么做吗? 就这么抛下古思伦?
Is this something ubba would do? Abandon guthrum?
为了替兄弟报仇, 会的, 只要他的巫师那边说得通
To avenge his brother, yes. If guided by his sorcerer's story.
他还有个巫师?
He has a sorcerer?
这巫师是做什么的?
And what does this sorcerer do?
施法? 行巫术?
Cast spells? Perform magic?
他出谋划策, 大人
He advises, lord.
他寻找征兆
He looks for omens.
- 吉兆凶兆都看    - 哦, 简直是无稽之谈
- Signs, good and bad. - Oh, what nonsense.
大人, 奇迹若不是魔法, 又是什么?
What are miracles, lord, if not magic?
奇迹是天主所为, 非人力所及
Miracles are performed by god, not man.
丹麦人也这么说 他们认为预兆是众神赐予的礼物
Danes say the same. Omens are gifts from gods.
他们错了
And they are mistaken.
是谁示意乌巴去爱尔兰的?
Who gave the sign for ubba to go to Ireland?
- 是你们的神还是他们的神? - 只有一个神
- The hand of your god or theirs? - There's one god.
那他一定也跟丹麦人说过话
Then he must have spoken to the Danes.
乌巴如今去了爱尔兰
With ubba now in Ireland,
古思伦就得决定他是否要单独迎战了
guthrum must now decide whether he will fight alone.
他不会单独出战的
He won't fight alone.
不是说他赢不了
Not that he couldn't win.
他会怕折损太多手下
He will fear losing too many of his men.
是的, 大人
Yes, lord.
我明白了一件事...
I am learning...
这些异教徒只顾自身利益
That the heathen cares only for personal gain.
丹麦人绝对受不了我喝的粥
A Dane could never suffer my gruel.
应该是"肉汤", 大人
"Broth," lord.
郡长乌特雷德, 你和米尔德丝过得好吗?
You are happy, ealdorman uhtred, with mildrith?
很好, 大人, 她是个好妻子
Yes, lord. She's a good wife.
不过要是早知道我得欠两千先令, 我当初绝不会娶她
Though I never would have married her had I known I'd owe 2,000 shillings.
而且每年还在涨
Which increases yearly.
您一句话, 这债就能免了
On your word, the debt can be lifted.
我凭什么让教会少收两千先令?
Why should I deny the church 2,000 shillings?
- 我根本不知道还有这债   - 这又不是什么秘密
- I wasn't aware I'd owe it. - It is not a secret.
正是牺牲与忏悔, 让我们有别于异教徒
Sacrifice and penance are what separate us from the heathen.
我有我的肉汤, 你有你的债
I have my broth, you have your debt.
威塞克斯需要一支军队, 你同意吗?
Wessex needs an army, would you agree?
一支常设的强大军队
A permanent and formidable army.
是，大人
Yes, lord.
英格兰一旦真正建立起来，就需要一支更强大的军队
England, when it finally emerges, shall need a greater army.
驻军将达数千之众，全都需要粮饷
Garrisons of many thousands of men, all will need feeding and payment.
我打算让所有地主
It is my intention that all landowners shall contribute
共同承担这支军队及其将领的给养
to the feeding of this army and its commanders.
我还需要将领，乌特雷德
And I will need commanders, uhtred.
像罗马那些伟大统帅一样的人
Men like the great generals of Rome.
把这笔债当作一份馈赠吧
Look upon the debt as a gift.
这是你向威塞克斯和英格兰证明忠心的机会
A means of proving your devotion to wessex and to england.
- 要是当初有人告诉我实情……   - 我看你还戴着那枚护身符
- If I'd been told the truth from... - You still wear the amulet, I see.
为了铭记拉格纳伯爵
To remind me of Earl ragnar.
你为何不陪你妻子去教堂？为何不向天主祈祷？
Why do you not attend church with your wife? Why do you not pray to god?
天主创造了我身边的一切
God created everything that surrounds me.
田野、河流、森林，这片大地就是我的教堂
The fields, rivers, the forests. The land is my church.
我每天都在祈祷，大人……
And I pray each day, lord...
默默地祈祷
In silence.
他是管不住的
He cannot be tamed.
但他是可以信任的
But he can be trusted.
我不会彻底放弃他
I will not abandon him completely.
我想他还有用处
He may have a use, I'm sure.
听好了，沃勒姆已经失守
Hear me now. Wareham has fallen.
我们立刻出兵
We march at once.
每个人都要按国王的命令行事
Every man is to be ready to do as the king asks.
丹麦人已经攻占了那座要塞
The Danes have taken the fortress.
沃勒姆已经陷落 立刻出发
Wareham has fallen. We march at once.
今天结束之前, 我们可能就踩在血水和内脏里了
We could be slipping in blood and entrails before the day is out.
别管他 够所有人分的
Leave him. There's enough for everyone.
古思伦, 他们来了
Guthrum, they're here.
撒克逊大军正在集结
The Saxon army is gathering.
- 是阿尔弗雷德吗? - 是
- Is it Alfred? - Yes.
要塞修缮好了吗, 防守稳固吗?
Is the fortress repaired and secure?
很稳固
Yes
很好, 他不会进攻
Good. He will not attack.
他不需要进攻, 他知道我们几天之内就会断粮
He doesn't need to. He knows we'll be hungry within days.
- 我们可以去劫掠  - 不行
- We can raid. - No.
他会把周边村子的粮仓清空
He will empty all the grain stores in the surrounding villages.
我发现这些教堂房间出奇地安静祥和
I have found these church rooms to be strangely quiet and peaceful.
大人, 我带着兵马跋山涉水横穿英格兰, 不是来这儿挨饿的
Lord, I didn't march my men halfway across england for them to starve.
- 我去城墙巡查          - 拉格纳, 我们是来打仗的
- I shall be on the ramparts. - We came for war, ragnar.
但乌巴背信弃义
But ubba has reneged.
- 他是去为兄弟报仇     - 但你在这里
- To avenge his brother. - But you are here.
你不该去为你父亲报仇吗?
Should you not be avenging your father?
- 时机未到     - 是啊
- When the time is right. - Yes.
时机未到
When the time is right.
我们已经迈出了进攻威塞克斯的第一步
We have taken the first steps against wessex.
但乌巴的离开让我们实力大损
But ubba has left us weak.
他把我们所有人都置于险地
He put all of our lives at risk.
所以在乌巴回来之前
So until ubba returns,
我们必须谈和
we have to make peace.
所以如果你在那里的话...
So if you are there...
罗马的天主
God of Rome
来砍死我啊
Strike me down.
我想也不会
I thought not.
我们来这里, 是要让他们看清楚我们有多少人
We are here to show them how many we are.
我们来这里, 是要让他们看清楚我们有多少人!
We are here to show them how many we are!
我们有天主同在
That we are here with god.
这片土地是我们的
And that this is our land.
我们有天主同在!
That we are here with god!
这片土地是我们的!
And this is our land!
这是我们的土地!
This is our land!
我们的威塞克斯!
Our wessex!
这是我们的英格兰!
This is our england!
任何敢来抢夺的异教徒杂种, 我们都要杀光他们!
And we shall murder any heathen bastard that tries to take it!
- 他们想谈判, 大人     - 我知道他们想要什么
- They wish to talk, lord. - I know what they want.
他们想拖时间
They want time.
奥达, 带上你的卫兵跟我去, 利奥弗里克, 你也来
Odda, with your guards, you shall go with me. Leofric, you as well.
- 还有塞尔比克斯神父   - 是, 大人
- And father selbix. - Yes, lord.
利奥弗里克，你觉得那座要塞怎么样?
Leofric, What do you make of the fortress?
看起来相当坚固, 大人
It looks strong enough, lord.
没有缺口, 也没有明显损毁
No breach. No signs of lasting damage.
如果我们强攻呢?
And if we attacked?
我们会损失惨重
We would suffer.
能打进去就算走运了, 大人
We'd be lucky to see the inside, lord.
早上好, 阿尔弗雷德国王
Good morning, king Alfred.
丹麦人古思伦
Guthrum of the Danes.
我现在也是国王了, 东盎格利亚之王
I, too, am a king now, of east anglia.
不必行礼
You don't need to bow.
我来开门见山
I will begin.
我提议停战
I propose a truce.
古思伦伯爵, 要想停战, 你必须再次离开威塞克斯
For any truce to occur, Earl guthrum, you must leave wessex once again.
- 若我拒绝呢? - 我们便将你团团围困
- And if I refuse? - We surround you.
是啊, 你们围住的不过是一座小堡垒
Yes, you surround a small fortress,
但我们丹麦人围住的是你整个王国, 话虽如此
but we Danes surround your entire kingdom. That said,
我已决定从海路撤离
I've decided I shall leave by sea.
因此我要派人去调船
Therefore, I will send for ships.
- 要多少船? - 不超过十五艘
- How many ships? - No more than 15.
好吧
Very well.
你的船有一个月时间抵达
Your ships have one month to arrive.
- 时间不够    - 只供应一个月的食物和麦酒
- Not enough time. - Food and ale for one month only,
否则你就走路滚回东盎格利亚
or you will walk back to east anglia.
那我就调两百艘船来, 希望在我们饿死之前能到
Then I'll send for 200 ships and hope they arrive before we starve.
- 一个月根本不够      - 这是我的底线
- One month is not enough. - That is my limit.
你夺不回这座堡垒, 你心里清楚
You cannot take back the fortress. You know this.
食物和麦酒只供应一个月, 不会再多了
Food and ale for one month, no more.
到那时候, 海上的风暴也该来了
By which time, the sea storms will have arrived.
- 那是主赐的风暴    - 我们会在一个月内离开
- God's storms. - We will be gone within a month,
从食物和麦酒送达之日起算
beginning upon the delivery of food and ale.
乌特雷德, 祈祷结束后来见我
Uhtred, you will come to me following prayers.
- 是, 大人
- 塞尔比克斯神父, 你陪我一同祈祷
- Yes, lord. - Father selbix, you will pray with me.
是, 大人
Yes, lord.
请坐
Please sit.
多谢, 大人
Thank you, lord.
我有件事要交给你, 神父
I have a task for you, father.
大人请说
You only have to speak it.
作为和平的保证, 你将被送去做人质, 一共十人
As a guarantee of the peace, you will be given up as a hostage, one of ten.
丹麦人那边也会交出十人作为交换
The Danes, too, will give ten in exchange.
大人, 异教徒不把神父当回事
Lord, the pagans do not value priests.
你还不如送头猎犬过去呢
You might just as well offer a hound.
我听说古思伦对我们的信仰颇感好奇
I hear guthrum is curious about our faith.
我希望你去做他的老师
I would like you to become his teacher.
给他传道授业
Provide instruction.
要是他不愿意学呢?
And if he refuses to be a student?
那就坚持下去
Then persist.
用你一贯的方式, 温和, 带点幽默
Gently with humour, as is your manner.
你要清楚...
Make no mistake...
只要古思伦愿意受洗
Should guthrum ever consent to being baptised,
这场战争就结束了
then this war is over.
英格兰就是我们的了
England is ours.
你做的将是真正的天主的事业
This would be truly god's work you do.
恕我直言, 大人
Forgive me, lord,
我心里确实害怕
but I cannot help but feel afraid.
他们对待神父可不只是杀了了事
They are not content to simply kill a priest.
恐惧人人都有
Fear is within all of us.
勇气也是
As is strength.
大人, 等休战破裂, 我上阵杀敌还更有用
Lord, I'd be more useful as a warrior for when the truce fails.
休战还能撑一段时间
Oh, the truce will hold for a time.
在此期间, 你将是我安插在那座堡垒里的眼线
And in that time, you will be my eyes and ears inside the fortress.
- 监听什么? - 乌巴的消息
- Listening for what? - For ubba.
一旦听说他回来, 你就想办法逃出来
If and when you hear of his return, you will escape.
- 要是我被锁链拴着呢? - 我们的人会解散
- And if I'm in chains? - Our men shall disband.
让他们去种地
There are fields to work.
我会在山丘上建一座烽火台, 你逃出来就点火
I'll build a beacon on the hill. You'll escape and light the fire.
大人, 您知道逃跑几乎是不可能的
Lord, you know that escape will be near impossible.
乌巴一旦回来, 人质就会被杀, 丹麦人随即会发动进攻
If ubba returns, the hostages will be killed and the Danes will attack.
一看到烽火燃起
Upon sight of this beacon being lit,
其他烽火也会相继点燃, 威塞克斯全境都会集结备战
other fires will start. Wessex will be called to arms.
- 如果我拒绝去做人质呢? - 会有另一个人去点那把火
- If I refuse to become a hostage? - Another man shall light the beacon.
你为何就是不肯接纳我?
Why can't you accept me?
我从未说过半句谎话, 为何总要考验我?
I've been nothing but truthful. Why am I always put to the test?
你为何不给你的国王应有的尊重?
Why do you not show your king respect that is due?
因为你, 不管什么地方来的乌特雷德
Because you, uhtred of wherever,
根本没把我当你的国王, 也没把我的天主当你的天主
you do not see me as your king. You do not see my god as your god.
- 大人? - 我还没说完
- My lord? - I am not finished with you yet.
古思伦一直在等乌巴从爱尔兰回来的消息
Guthrum is waiting to hear of ubba's return from Ireland.
我需要尽早得知此事, 越快越好, 而你...
I need to know when this occurs, sooner rather than later. You...
是唯一有可能最先带回这个消息的人
Are the only man who could possibly provide this information sooner.
没错, 你可能会死
Yes, it is possible that you will die,
但我们大概都难逃一死
but it is likely that we shall all die.
你要去丹麦人那里
You will go to the Danes.
以什么身份去, 是撒克逊人质
How you go, as a Saxon hostage
还是维京勇士, 是你的选择
or as a viking warrior, becomes your choice.
我会照你说的做
I'll do as you ask.
但如果我被扣押期间孩子降生，我请求你给我带个信
But if my child is born while I'm captive, I ask that you send word.
当然
Of course.
若你死在被扣押期间，放心，你的债也随你一起消了
And should you die as a captive, rest assured, your debt shall die with you.
他们会善待我们吗？
Will they treat us well?
你是他们中的一员
You are one of them.
我若是他们的一员，为何还要做人质？
If I am one of them, then why am I a hostage?
只要停战协议还在，他们就会善待我们
They'll treat us well for as long as the truce holds.
- 若协议破裂呢？- 他们会把我们全杀了，
- If it fails? - They'll kill us all,
从神父开始，哈！
starting with the priest. Heh!
我已坦然接受，我已准备好了
I've made my peace. I am ready.
晚上好，愿主保佑你们
Good evening and god bless you all.
可怜的人
Poor wretches.
那我们呢，神父，我们又算什么？
And us, father, what are we?
我们是有福之人，大人，我们认识天主
We are fortunate, lord. We know god.
不过坦白说，我不急着去见他
Although granted, I'm in no hurry to meet him.
愿天主也这么想
Let us pray he feels the same.
阿门
Amen.
就这群乌合之众，还让那么多人胆寒？
Is this rabble what so many are afraid of?
来来来，他们跟孩子没两样
Come. They're like children.
够了，够了！
Enough. Enough!
他们暂时是我们的客人
They are our guests for a while.
只有一条规矩
There's one rule only.
天黑之后，
At nightfall,
所有人集合，到教堂里睡觉
you will gather and sleep at the church.
门会被封死
The doors will be barred.
天亮之后, 你们可以自由行走、交谈、跳跃、交欢、携带武器
At daybreak, you will then be free to walk, talk, jump, hump, carry weapons.
我的人奉命不会杀你们...
My men have orders not to kill you...
除非你们该死
Unless you deserve to be killed.
我是古思伦
I am guthrum.
总有一天, 我将成为你们的国王
And one day, I shall be your king.
你们听懂我说的了吗?
Do you understand what I have said?
你们都要说:"是的, 大人"
You will all say, "yes, lord."
是的, 大人
Yes, lord.
我没听见
I did not hear you.
我们听懂了, 大人
I understand you, lord.
也许我会把你作为礼物送给乌巴
Maybe I will make a present of you to ubba.
- 要是他从爱尔兰回来的话       - 他可能不会回来, 也说不定
- Should he ever return from Ireland. - He may not. That's possible.
但到那时他的人就会成为我的人
But then his men will become my men,
我会亲手杀了你, 以此向他致敬
and I will honour him by killing you myself.
也许用箭
With arrows, perhaps.
- 拉格纳·拉格纳森    - 在这
- Ragnar ragnarson. - Here.
你对这人很熟, 让他别出现在我眼前
You know this one well. Keep him out of my sight.
把他们带去教堂, 给他们吃的
Take them to the church. Feed them.
现在你们到了该待的地方
Now you are where you belong.
现在我和我兄弟在一起了
Now I'm with my brother.
我会让你重新感受身为丹麦人是什么滋味, 让你留下来
I will remind you what it is like to be a Dane and make you stay.
布丽达也在这里
Brida's here.
我梦到过你, 小狐狸
I dream about you, Vixen.
听到这话我一点都不意外
I'm not surprised to hear it.
你长大了, 哈哈
You've grown up. Heh, heh.
你该知道我现在跟着拉格纳, 他是我的男人
You should know I'm with ragnar now. He's my man.
这是好事
That's good.
你也该知道, 我成婚了
You should know that I am married.
成婚了?
Married?
- 你真的长大了  - 他成婚了?
- You have grown up. - He's married?
对, 他成婚了
Yes, he is married.
时间过得比我想的快多了
Time is moving quicker than I thought.
今晚, 我们喝个痛快
Tonight, we get drunk.
必须的
We must.
- 晚上我得呆在教堂里
- 不, 今晚我们喝个痛快
- I need to be inside the church. - No, tonight we get drunk.
我亲自带你去教堂
I'll take you to the church myself.
或者喝倒在哪儿就睡哪儿, 哈哈
Or we sleep where we fall, ha, ha.
还有, 呃...
And, uh...
我们得谈谈将来的事
We must talk of the future.
我们是桨手!
We are oarsmen!
乌特雷德, 给我划! 啊!
Uhtred, pull for me. Aah!
- 我去撒泡尿, 马上回来  - 他会回来的
- I need to piss. I'll return. - He'll return.
拉格纳? 拉格纳?
Ragnar? Ragnar?
我很久没这么开心地笑过了
I haven't laughed so much in a long time.
那说明你活得不够痛快
Then you haven't been living.
或者像拉文说的, "明日我们便死"
Or as ravn would say, "tomorrow we die."
他什么时候说过这话?
When did he ever say that?
你去劈柴的时候
When you were out chopping wood.
我是真的要去撒尿
Well, I actually do need to piss.
哈哈, 你该做的是少喝点酒
Ha, ha, what you need to do is to stop drinking.
明天我们就要死了
Tomorrow we die.
- 他很高兴见到你   - 我也想他了
- He's happy to see you. - I've missed him.
我想念你们俩
I miss you both.
她是你的妻子?
Are you his wife?
我跟他在一起
I'm with him.
- 她漂亮吗? - 嗯
- Is she beautiful? - Mm.
她叫米尔德丝, 很漂亮
Her name's mildrith. Yes, she is beautiful.
她怀了我的孩子
She carries my child.
是谁决定你们成婚的?
Who decided you should marry?
阿尔弗雷德
Alfred.
我在威塞克斯得到了我想要的那片土地
I have the land I asked for in wessex.
你向阿尔弗雷德宣誓效忠
You swear an oath to Alfred.
你为阿尔弗雷德娶妻, 土地也是阿尔弗雷德赐给你的
You marry for Alfred. You have land given to you by Alfred.
你的妻子怀了你的骨肉
Your wife carries your child.
可阿尔弗雷德竟然把你当人质献出去?
And yet you're given up as a hostage by Alfred?
你是探子吗, 乌特雷德?
Are you a spy, uhtred?
一旦乌巴回来的风声传出, 我就得设法逃脱
At the first sign of ubba returning, I am to escape.
但我心里清楚, 乌巴一回来, 那些人质就会被杀
But I know that when ubba returns, the hostages will be killed.
阿尔弗雷德不喜欢我
Alfred's not fond of me.
拒绝他
Refuse him.
拒绝当人质, 加入我们
Refuse to be a hostage. Join us.
我该问你的, 乌特雷德
I should ask you, uhtred.
不是说结果会有什么不同, 但我该问你的
Not that it matters, but I should ask.
布丽达现在跟我在一起, 你有意见吗?
Is it a problem to you that brida's with me now?
哈, 没有, 我很高兴
Ha, ha, no. I'm happy about it.
- 我发誓  - 好吧
- I swear. - All right.
再说她也不在乎你怎么想
Not that she cares what you think.
反正不管你同不同意我也会睡她, 不过...
I would hump her regardless. But...
是带着...带着情意的
With... with affection.
- 也是经过我允许的     - 我知道
- And with my permission. - I know.
你知道乌特雷德快当父亲了吗?
Do you know uhtred's to be a father?
- 什么时候? - 听说快了
- When? - Soon, I'm told.
你想去看孩子出生?
You would want to see it?
想, 我希望能回去陪我的妻儿
Yes. I hope to return to my wife and child.
拉格纳
Ragnar.
我会和你一起为父亲报仇, 基尔坦会付出代价的
I'll be with you to avenge our father. Kjartan will pay.
你几个月前就该带着布丽达来找我了
You should have joined me months ago with brida.
我宣过誓
I'd sworn an oath.
对一个烂透了的撒克逊王
To a poxy Saxon king.
乌巴要我的命, 我无处可去
Ubba wanted me dead. There was nowhere else to go.
我一直在想那天晚上在林子里的事
I've thought about that night in the woods.
- 你当时可以选择做撒克逊人还是丹麦人  - 不, 我已经宣过誓了
- You had a choice to be Saxon or Dane. - No, I had sworn an oath.
你本该来找我的
You should have joined me.
我会和你一起去杀基尔坦
I'll be with you to kill kjartan.
我带你去教堂, 送你上床休息
I will take you to the church, to your bed.
- 怎么了? - 是个儿子, 夫人
- What is it? - It's a son, lady.
漂亮的小子
A handsome boy.
你将是乌特雷德, 乌特雷德之子
You will be uhtred, son of uhtred.
早安，乌特雷德
Good morning, uhtred.
早安，神父
Good morning, father.
又下雨了
Raining again.
每天都一个样
One day seems like the next.
是啊
It does.
不过至少我们还活着，还能感受这雨
Still, at least we're alive to feel it.
你跟古思伦谈得怎么样?
How are your conversations with guthrum?
他信天主了吗?
Is he a Christian yet?
我相信时机快到了，真的
I believe the time is near, I do.
我常常让他一个人在教堂里静思
I often leave him to contemplate alone in church.
古思伦喜欢沉思的是战争和王国
Guthrum likes to contemplate war and kingdoms.
天国的荣光也等着他来分享
The kingdom of heaven is his to share.
我已经告诉他了
I've told him.
一个人是可以改变的，乌特雷德
A man can change, uhtred.
前行吧，愿主赐福于你
Onward. God bless you.
祝你度过美好的一天
May you enjoy a good day.
多谢，神父
Thank you, father.
祂是万王之王
He is the king of kings.
能够成就无比伟大的事
Capable of great, great things.
比如什么?
Such as what?
比如奇迹
Such as miracles.
奇迹?
Miracles?
比如什么?
Such as what?
比如您，大人
Such as you, lord.
您就是一个奇迹
You are a miracle.
祂让你刚强而不失仁慈
He has made you strong yet merciful.
祂...
He has...
让你自豪而不失谦逊
Made you proud yet humble.
祂让你渴望学习
He has made you eager to learn.
祂赐给你自由意志
He has given you free will,
希望你能鼓起勇气, 将祂置于一切之上
hoping that you will find the courage to choose him above all else.
我相信, 我真心相信
And I believe, I truly believe,
祂会得到回报
he will be rewarded.
- 我有消息要带给古思伦    - 他在教堂里
- I have a message for guthrum. - He's in the church.
- 大人, 我可以说吗  - 直说
- Lord, may I speak? - Freely.
乌巴和他的军队从爱尔兰回来了
Ubba and his army have returned from Ireland.
他们正在北边的塞文河一带登岸
They are coming ashore north of here at the severn.
我的舰队在哪儿?
And my fleet is where?
几天前已从伦敦出发, 快到了
They left lundene several days ago and are nearly here.
每一艘船都会到, 每一个人都会跟着你
Every last ship will be here. Every man will be with you.
这是好消息
That is good news.
我送你去你们的天堂
I dispatch you to your heaven.
不用谢我
No need to thank me.
神父
Father.
乌巴回来了?
Ubba has returned?
他们说了吗?
Did they say?
弟兄们, 休战结束了
Men, the peace is over.
备战!
Prepare for battle.
把撒克逊人质全部杀掉
The Saxon hostages, kill them all.
- 抓住他! - 抓住他!
- Catch him! - Get him.
把他剁碎!
Cut him to pieces!
杀了他!
Kill him!
放他走
Leave him.
我说放他走!
I say leave him!
拉格纳
Ragnar.
请让开
Please step aside.
你知道所有人质都得死
You know all of the hostages have to die.
那就杀了他
Then kill him.
你尽管去杀他, 但你得先杀了我
You're welcome to kill him. But you have to kill me first.
没有这件事的话我会很开心的
I could happily manage without this.
他是撒克逊人, 是叛徒, 是敌人
He's a Saxon. He's a traitor. He's an enemy.
那你要过去, 就得先杀了我
Well, to get to him, you have to kill me.
我的手下不会跟着你走
My men, they will not follow you.
我最后再给你一次机会
I will give you one last charity.
放他走, 不给马
Release him without a horse.
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
我不知道说什么好
I have no words.
你走吧, 去看看你的孩子, 去
You should go. Go and see your child. Go.
好
Yes.
我会找到你的
I'll be with you.
你们两个都是
Both of you.